Lottie Pozniak papers 1930-1998 CPAA 86-09
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University, New Britain
Lottie Pozniak papers
1930-1998
Pozniak, Lottie
CPAA 86-09
5 boxes (3.5 linear ft.)
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University
Lottie Pozniak (Kaminski) was born in Hartford, Connecticut to the first generation of Polish Americans. She was very active in many Polish American cultural organizations. During World War II she participated in selling war bonds and organized many events to benefit troops. After the war she became a participant and promoter of Polish history and culture. She received many awards and recognitions for her work. The collection richly illustrates with printed and visual material Mrs. Pozniak's activities and the Polish American community in Connecticut.
Biographical Note
Lottie Pozniak (Kaminski) was born in Hartford, Connecticut to a family of Polish immigrants. She was a second generation Polish American, that came to maturity before the WWII. From her childhood Lottie was involved in Polish community, starting with her parent's involvement in the PNA and Polish National Home activities. Lottie dvoted her life to preserve and present Poland and Polish culture to her American friends. In her teenage years Lottie became very active in "Gwiazda" Dramatic Club, which promoted and fostered Polish tradition and culture through different dramatic works. Mrs. Pozniak studied advanced Polish history and language at Columbia University. She was involved in various organizations and spent hundred of hours on volunteer work, such as selling War bonds, entertaining troops, directing blood drives, and working with military personnel who had lost their sight in combat. After the war, Lottie Pozniak continued her involvement in various projects. She was still active in the Gwiazda club in addition to co-hosting radio programs and being a member of the Parish Ladies Guild of SS. Cyril and Methodious Church, Polish Women's Alliance, Polish National Alliance, Ladies Auxilliary of the Polish Legion of American Veterans, and PAC of Connecticut. Since the late 1960's Lottie has been involved in the Polish Cultural Club of Greater Hartford. She has romoted Polish culture by organizing and presenting artifacts and educational materials for various schools and libraries. She organized the Polish booth at the Connecticut Historical Society's ethnic day, Civic Center Food Fair, International Day at CCSU, and the Wadsworth Atheneum Museum in Hartford. For her active involvement she has received numerous recognitions and awards. Currently Lottie continues to promote her cultural heritage.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The collection consists of printed and visual material related to Polish history, culture, and cultural undertakings in Connecticut. Collection of photographs illustrates activities of Lottie Pozniak and organizations to which she belonged. Printed material consists of Mrs. Pozniak's documents related to Polish and Polish American issues and her active membership in various organizations.
The collection is open for research.
Most of the material in the collection was donated by Mrs. Lottie Pozniak in 1986. After that several donations were made with material collected after the first donation, in 1991, 1998, 2001 and 2003.
Search Terms
Lottie Pozniak; Polish Americans -- Connecticut.; Immigrants -- Connecticut.; Polish Americans -- Connecticut -- Societies, etc.; Polish Americans -- Connecticut -- Hartford.; Pamphlets.; Photographs.; Clippings.; Correspondence.; Scrapbook.; Music notes.
Related Material
For related material see the following collections:
Polish Cultural Club of Greater Hartford CPAA 86-30
Arrangement
Material in the collection is arranged by date.
Container List
[The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Lottie Pozniak testimonial by Prof. Stanislaus A. Blejwas., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Lottie Pozniak's awards, certificates of appreciation., 1958-1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Newspaper clippings related to Lottie Pozniak., 1960-1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence., 1966-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- The Kaminski family history - Lottie's parents, includes photographs., undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Polska, a textbook for the Polish language and history class, used by Lottie., 1934 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Letter from United States Information Agency., [1989?] (Box 1, Folder 7)
- 35th Annual ACPC Convention, keynote address by Adele Wilzack., 1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Polish Cultural Club of Greater Hartford, various publications., 1980-1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- ACPC Annual Report., 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Ludwik J. Pyrtek, MD obituary in: Surgical ByLine, Hartford Hospital, CT., Dec. 1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Polish National Home, Hartford, CT - booklets, clippings. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Polish culture and folklore - brochures, postcards from Poland., 1970's (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Polish traditions, customs, food - clippings, pamphlets. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Polish American heritage packet: excerpted curriculum packet, Yonkers Public Schools., 1994 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Polish scouting in Connecticut (clippings)., 1930's (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Clippings related to Polish and Polish American issues from Polish and American press. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Kosciuszko and Pulaski their history - clippings. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- History of Poland and Polonia - various pamphlets and clippings. (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Clippings related to Polonia in Connecticut. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- American Institute of Polish Culture, Miami, Florida, programs, brochures. (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Social events related to Polonia in Connecticut - announcements, programs. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Scial events out of state - announcements, programs. (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Various menue - Polish Oceanliner Batory. (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Music notes, Polish dances, pt.1. (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Music notes, Polish dances, pt.2. (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Various anniversary publication and information on material separated. (Box 1, Folder 27)
- "Gwiazda" Dramatic Club production of the Polish Radio Program during WWII, 2 photographs., 1940's (Box 2, Folder 1)
- "Gwiazda" Dramatic Club production during WWII, 6 photographs., 1942 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- "Gwiazda" Dramatic Club performances, 5 photographs., 1960-1970 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- War bond testimonies, photographs, certificates., 1940's (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Jaselka Polskie and Wigilia w Polsce, two plays performed by Gwiazda group. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Lottie Pozniak with officers of the Polish Girls Club, 2 photographs., 1930 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- "Gwiazda" Polish Darmatic Club, Minute Book., 1943-1949 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- "Gwiazda" Polish Dramatic Club, constitution., undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- "Gwiazda" Polish Dramatic Club, correspondence., 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- "Gwiazda" Polish Dramatic Club, anniversary publication., 1970, 1980, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Plays parformed by Gwiazda: "Jestesmy w wojsku", "Te diabelki", by J.J.S., published in Adams, Massachusetts., 1940's (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Ladies Guild, S.S. Cyril and Methodius Church, Hartford, CT, anniversary publications, reports. (Box 2, Folder 12)
- United Polish Societies, Hartford, CT anniversary publications., 1970, 1971, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- ACPC publication: All American and mighty proud of that Polish name, pamphlet by Thaddeus Maliszewski., [1987] (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Polish American Congress, CT Division, financial report., 1956 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Clippings, cultural events., 1960-1980 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Crazy Horse, "Carving a dream" by Robb DeWall., 1992 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Crazy Horse, Ziolkowski-Korczak, anniversary pamphlet., 1982-1988 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Crazy Horse, Ziolkowski-Korczak, articles, clippings, post cards., 1980-1990 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Crazy Horse Memorial, correspondence., 1998-2000 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- "Crazy Horse and Korczak" by Robb DeWall., 1982 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Publications related to immigrants and ethnic groups for secondary schools. (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Student paper: Eastern European Easter Eggs: a folk art study of pysanky., 1992 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Pulaski Day in Hartford, Governor and Mayor proclamation., 1988 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Polish Constitution Day celebration in Connecticut., 1984, 1985, 1990, 1997, 2000, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Congressional Record, Polish Constitution Day, speech by Hon. B.J. Monkiewicz, May 3, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- 50th Anniversary of the invasion of Poland, Polish National Home, Hartford, CT., Sep. 1989 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- The 2nd World War started September 1st, 1939 - 50 anniversary of the Invasion of Poland, pamphlet., 1989 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Sen. Barbara Kennelly resolution about Polish-German border, H.Conn.Res.273., 1990 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Political posters brought from Poland., 1989 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Books: Polskie pamiatki z Loretto, Rozaniec z Ojcem Swietym., 1983, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Prayer books. (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Najwiekszy zbior piosenek polskich, compiled by Edmund Liszka, New Britain, CT., 1948 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Szary proch: powiesc wspolczesna, by Marja Rodziewiczowna, Milwaukie, WI., 1908 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Polish Women's Alliance, pamphlets. (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Photo album, various cultural events in Hartford, CT., 1980's (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Collection of pins related to anniversary events. (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Scrapbook - Polish Dramatic Club Gwiazda [clippings, pictures, programs]., 1932-1970 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Photographs - Polish Home Directors; Mrs. Mary Jasiak Kaminski maid of honor in 1914; Mrs. Mary Jasiak Kaminski as bridesmaid at a wedding in Hartford in 1914; wedding of Gladys Kaminski Rolka in 1925 (aunt of Lottie Pozniak); Harcerstwo organized by Polish National Alliance (PNA) in 1939 - Lottie Pozniak, picture taken in front of SS. Cyryl and Methodius in Hartford., 1914-1939 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Poster - The Future of Crazy Horse Memorial., 1982 (Box 4, Folder 3)